Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- 1529-1907, Part I
  - Title: "Papeles s de Flon." Places: Mexico City, Puebla. Description: Diverse documents related to the administrative career of Manuel de Flon, intendant of Puebla. Includes "Copia de los méritos del señor don Bartolomé de Flon y Zurbarán, primer Conde de la Cadena," and correspondence between Manuel de Flon and the Mexican viceroys. 1796-1803 (Box 24, Folder 317, Reel 22)
  - Title: Documents on the viceregal assesor. Places: Madrid, San Ildefonso, Aranjuez. Description: Four documents: copies of three royal decrees, and a note, concerning the duties and prerogatives of the viceregal assessor. 1796-1804 (Box 24, Folder 318, Reel 22)
  - Title: Letters to Juan Nepomuceno Quintero. Place: Maltrata. Description: Three letters addressed to Juan Nepomuceno Quintero, lawyer for the Royal Audiencia of Mexico and councilman of the Puebla cabildo. Includes: a letter written by his son, Manuel Antonio, sending a present of fruits (22 December 1796); a letter by his son, Juan Pascual Bautista, sending a present of fruits (8 May 1797); and a letter by Gabriel Angl. [Angeles?] commenting on the affairs of the Puebla cabildo (30 January 1806). Also includes the envelope from one of the letters. 1796-1806 (Box 24, Folder 319, Reel 22)
  - Title: "Libro donde se asientan las elecciones de los señores rectores, consiliarios y tesoreros del Colegio Y.V. y M. Santa María de Todos los Santos. Año de 1796." Place: Mexico City. Description: Book containing agreements on election of authorities and administration of the College of Santa María de Todos los Santos in Mexico City. 1796-1842 (Box 24, Folder 320, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decree and laws. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree, addressed to the viceroy of Mexico, approving the measures taken by him for the renovation of the churches of Tlahuac and Xochimilco. Includes transcripts of two laws concerning the administration of money from the Royal Treasury and ecclesiastical rents for the reconstruction of churches. 1797 Jul 20 (Box 25, Folder 321, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Copy of a royal decree, addressed to the viceroy of Mexico, ordering the members of the Confraternity of the Holy Sacrament and the Conception, founded in the town of San Guillermo Totolapa, to formulate new ordinances for that Confraternity. 1797 Aug 26 (Box 25, Folder 322, Reel 23)
  - Title: Title of commissary. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a title of commissary of the Santa Hermandad. Details duties to prevent crime and delinquency. The text constitutes a form to be completed when nominating commissaries. 1797 Sep 19 (Box 25, Folder 323, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: San Ildefonso. Description: Copy of a royal decree regulating the nomination of ecclesiastical provisors and general vicaries. 1797 Sep 20 (Box 25, Folder 324, Reel 23)
  - Author: González del Campillo, Manuel Ignacio. Title: "Disertación sobre la edad necesaria para optar la canongía penitenciaria." Place: Puebla. Description: From an analysis of ecclesiastical and civil laws, Manuel Ignacio González del Campillo, canon of the Puebla cathedral chapter, examines the age required to be nominated penitenciary canon in this legal writ. 1797 Dec 29 (Box 25, Folder 325, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Colección de providencias tomadas en esta ciudad con motivo de la epidemia de viruelas que esta padeciendo desde octubre de este ano de 1797." Place: Puebla. Description: Copies of the ordinances issued by Viceroy Branciforte, the cabildo, and the bishop of Puebla to fight the smallpox epidemic in Puebla. 1797 (Box 25, Folder 326, Reel 23)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Copy of a legal writ related to the controversy between the juez de bienes de difuntos and the intendant of Puebla over the payment of alcabala tax by the administrator of the San Juan Bautista Ayotla hacienda, which was owned by José Duarte. [ca.1797] (Box 25, Folder 327, Reel 23)
  - Title: Regulations on missionaries. Place: Mexico City? Description: Copy of a document containing regulations on duties and privileges of missionaries in the Mexican viceroyalty. [ca.1797] (Box 25, Folder 328, Reel 23)
  - Title: Documents on the Tribunal de Bienes de difuntos. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of royal and viceregal decrees related to the administration of the Tribunal de Bienes de difuntos in the Mexican viceroyalty. There are two printed copies of an issue of the "Gazeta de México" (Wednesday 18 August 1802), which reproduced a royal decree on jurisdictional controversies between the Royal Audiencia and the Tribunal de Bienes de difuntos. 1797-1817 (Box 25, Folder 329, Reel 23)
  - Title: Documents on tithes. Place: Puebla. Description: Copies of several documents related to the administration of the ecclesiastical tithes in the bishopric of Puebla. 1798 (Box 25, Folder 330, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Arco triunfal en obsequio del excelentísimo señor don Miguel Azanza, virey governador y capitán general de esta Nueva España erigido para el día de su ingreso a esta ciudad por su muy noble y leal ayuntamiento de la Puebla de los Angeles. Año de 1798." Place: Puebla. Description: The construction of arches for the reception of civil and ecclesiastical dignitaries had a long tradition in the political culture of the Spanish empire. The arches were usually decorated with paintings, sculptures and poetic texts. These ornaments were to glorify and convey political and moral principles to the new rulers. The triumphal arch erected by the Puebla cabildo to receive Viceroy Miguel Azanza, duke of Santa Fe, is described in detail in this text, probably written by a councilman. 1798 (Box 25, Folder 331, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decrees by the King. Places: Madrid, San Lorenzo, San Ildefonso. Description: Copies, handwritten and printed, of several royal and viceregal decrees on the collection of funds to finance the Spanish army in the war against England. 1798 (Box 25, Folder 332, Reel 23)
  - Title: Text on patronage of chaplancies. Place: Mexico City? Description: This text argues that the king was the titular patron of chaplancies which formerly belonged to the Society of Jesus. [1798?] (Box 25, Folder 333, Reel 23)
  - Title: Documents on the ecclesiastical amortization. Places: Mexico, Spain. Description: Copies, handwritten and printed, of several royal and viceregal decrees on the payment and administration of the ecclesiastical amortization. 1798-1807 (Box 25, Folder 334, Reel 23)
  - Title: Viceregal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a decree by Miguel José de Azanza, viceroy of Mexico, ordering compliance with a royal decree which regulated the trials held at the end of terms in office of colonial authorities. Includes the royal decree issued on 24 August 1799. 1800 Mar 12 (Box 25, Folder 335, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree, issued on 2 December 1799, ordering that the reception for new bishops in their dioceses was to be paid for by "las rentas que tengan vencidas en sus respectivas yglecias." 1802 Nov 6 (Box 25, Folder 336, Reel 23)
  - Title: Royal decree and note. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree which enables Cleric Rafael López Moreno, who was a member of the regular clergy, to receive ecclesiastical nominations except from the cathedral chapters. There is also a short note commenting on the case of Temalcan's priest, who was ordained in spite of being abandoned by his parents when he was a child (expósito.). 1799 Dec 20 (Box 25, Folder 337, Reel 23)
  - Title: Legal notes. Place: Mexico City? Description: Legal notes related to the judicial proceedings of Bachellor Mateo Navarro to force the acceptance of his resignation as parish priest. [ca.1799] (Box 25, Folder 338, Reel 23)
  - Title: Documents related to the ecclesiastical subsidy. Place: Mexico. Description: Copies of several documents related to the collection and administration of the ecclesiastical subsidy for the Spanish crown. Includes copies of several viceregal decrees. 1799-1802 (Box 25, Folder 339, Reel 23)
  - Author: Guridi y Alcozer, José Miguel. Title: "Sermón panegírico que en obsequio de San Gregorio Taumaturgo." Place: Antequera, Oaxaca. Description: Copy of the sermon in honor of Saint Gregory, preached by José Miguel Guridi y Alcozer, at the proceedings held to fill the position of magisterial canonry for the cathedral of Antequera, Oaxaca. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 340, Reel 23)
  - Author: Guridi y Alcozer, José Miguel? Title: Sermon in honor of the Virgin of Remedies. Place: Puebla? Description: Copy of a sermon dedicated to the Virgin of Remedies, a devotion brought by the Spanish conquerors in the sixteenth century. The sermon describes the miraculous interventions of the Virgin in the Spanish conquest of Mexico. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 341, Reel 23)
  - Title: Petition by María Gertrudis Barragán. Place: Mexico City? Description: Petition by María Gertrudis Barragán, related to her judicial proceedings against Ursula Carrillo over defamation. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 342, Reel 23)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Puebla? Description: Legal writ related to the judicial proceedings against Dominican Joséf Zambrano, accused of unchastity. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 343, Reel 23)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Puebla? Description: Draft of a legal writ related to the dispute between Ramón Arana, treasurer of the college seminaries of Saint Peter and Saint John, and the rector of the College Seminar of Saint Paul, over the administration of the testamentary legacy of Manuel Fernández de Santa Cruz, bishop of Puebla. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 344, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Reparos que se ponen para benir en conocimiento de que a Su Magestad...no le tiene quenta la erección de la fábrica de artillería en este reino." Place: Spain. Description: Report which analyzed establishing an artillery factory in Orizaba. The author was opposed to the project because of its high cost to the Royal Treasury. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 345, Reel 23)
  - Title: Text on alcaldes mayores. Place: Mexico City? Description: Two copies of a text evaluating the performance of the alcaldes mayores in administering justice. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 346, Reel 23)
  - Title: Plan for military defenses. Place: Campeche? Description: Plan for the construction of military defenses on the coasts of Campeche and Sacatan. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 347, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Instrucción que se dio a don Gerónimo Marín." Place: Mexico City? Description: Copy of the instructions given [by the viceroy?] to Gerónimo Marín for the organization of the military defense of the Veracruz port against an attack by the British fleet. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 348, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Los ofiziales de la governazión según sus clases." Place: Mexico? Description: Detailed report on military officers in the Mexican viceroyalty. The officers are classified according to their ranks and places of residence. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 349, Reel 23)
  - Author: Marquis de la Compuesta. Title: Memorials on the Spanish empire. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of two memorials by the Marquis de la Compuesta, treasurer of the Royal Audiencia of Mexico, addressed to the King, proposing reforms in the administration, government, and economy of the Spanish empire. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 350, Reel 23)
  - Title: Text on viceregal amnesty. Place: Mexico City? Description: Text on the authority of the viceroys to pardon criminals. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 351, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Repartimiento de quentas de mesas y ministros en que anualmente aygan de entender y feneser." Place: Mexico City? Description: Report on the accounting reports (cuentas) that civil and ecclesiastical authorities were to send annually to the Royal Treasury in Mexico City. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 352, Reel 23)
  - Title: Text on unchaste clerics. Place: Mexico City?. Description: Text containing a description of the penalties assessed unchaste clerics. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 353, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Duda curiosa." Place: Mexico City. Description: Text commenting on a legal writ by Licenciate Juan de Ymas Esquer, lawyer for the Royal Audiencia of Mexico, on the administration of chaplancies. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 354, Reel 23)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Legal writ related to the judicial proceedings of Isabel Laureana, María Jacinta, and Juan Ignacio de la Vega Sotomayor, against their sister, Joséfa Clemente de San Juan, nun of the convent of the Conception in Mexico City, over the administration of the inheritance of their father, Lieutenant Juan Ignacio de la Vega Sotomayor. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 355, Reel 23)
  - Title: "Crisol del ministerio apostólico de propaganda fide en la provincia de Sonora." Place: Aconchi, Sonora. Description: An anonymous missionary of the Franciscan mission of Aconchi, Sonora, wrote this account of his experience in the evangelization of the native peoples in that region. The text is a manual for missionary work, and also a eulogy of the same. By comparing the work of the Apostles with that of the Franciscans, the author intended to encourage other friars to continue indoctrinating non-Christians, in spite of the difficulty of the work. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 356, Reel 24)
  - Title: "Quenta y razón de lo que produce el estanco y molino de la pólvora." Place: Mexico. Description: Report on the administration of the gunpowder mill. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 357, Reel 24)
  - Title: "Breve extracto de las propozisiones que el excelentísimo señor Duque de Linares dio orden a don Joséph Domingo Colarte." Place: Mexico City. Description: Text containing a summary of the proposals by the Duke of Linares, viceroy of Mexico, for developing commerce between Mexico and Peru. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 358, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Puebla? Description: Copy of a legal writ related to the judicial proceedings of Agustín José de Rojas, governor of the Confraternity of the Blessed Souls of the Purgatory, established in the town of Santa Cruz Tlacotepec, against Andrés and José Mariano de Luna, over the ownership of a plot of land named Ixtlacostiqui. [17--] (Box 25, Folder 359, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Draft of a short legal writ related to the intervention by members of the regular clergy in judicial proceedings. The text is addressed to the Mercedarian Manuel Uribe. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 360, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Legal writ commenting on the sentence issued by the attorney for the Royal Audiencia against the Mercedarian Miguel Gómez, who had been condemned to serve as a soldier in the Philippines or Cuba. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 361, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Puebla? Description: Legal writ related to a controversy over the use of city lands (ejido) in Puebla. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 362, Reel 24)
  - Author: Rousseau, Jean Jacques. Title: "Observaciones de Juan Jacobo Rouseau, ciudadano de Ginebra, sobre la respuesta que han hecho a su discurso." Place: Mexico? Description: Copy of the response by the French philosopher Jean Jacques Rousseau to the critics of his Discours on the social and cultural benefits accruing from the reestablishment of arts and sciences. This translation, which comes from the collection of the Puebla lawyer Juan Nepomuceno Quintero, documents the spread of Rousseau's ideas in Mexican colonial society. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 363, Reel 24)
  - Title: Contract for selling pulque. Place: Mexico City? Description: Copy of regulations given by the colonial administration to Juan Baptista Marichalar for the selling of pulque in Mexico City and its jurisdiction. Details the economic benefits which could accrue to Marichalar and the commercial restrictions under which he had to work. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 364, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal order by the King. Place: Naples? Description: Copy of a royal order which instructs tribunals of justice to print their sentences. The order is apparently related to the administration of justice in Naples, a territory under the Spanish dominion. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 365, Reel 24)
  - Author: Zevallos "minor." Title: Manual of rhetoric. Place: Mexico? Description: The study of rhetoric was part of the curricula in colonial colleges. This small pocket book, containing principles of rhetoric, was presumably written by a junior student for his personal use. Signed "Zevallos, minor." [17--] (Box 26, Folder 366, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Draft of a legal writ related to the proceedings of people of the town of Apatzingán, Michoacán, to obtain from the ecclesiastical authority, the approval of ordinances for the Confraternity of the Holy Sacrament founded in that town. [17--] (Box 26, Folder 367, Reel 24)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City. Description: Draft of a legal writ related to the proceedings of the Confraternity of the Holy Sacrament against the cathedral chapter of Mexico over the seating which the Confraternity should have in religious ceremonies held in the cathedral. [17--?] (Box 26, Folder 368, Reel 24)
  - Title: "Constituciones que se han de observar y estan conferidas entre los hermanos y esclavos de Cristo Señor Nuestro de la Espiración que se venera en la capilla que esta anexa a la yglesia parroquial de este pueblo y cabezera de Zampango de las minas." Place: Zampango de las minas? Description: Ordinances for the Confraternity of Christ established in the town of Zampango de las minas. Details duties of its members, such as attendance at religious ceremonies, assistance at funerals and burials, and collection of alms. [17--?] (Box 26, Folder 369, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree by Antonio Porcel, addressed to the viceroy of Mexico, dated 26 March 1800, stating that Antonio Velasco had been nominated to occupy a "ración de gracia" in the collegiate church of Guadalupe in Mexico City. 1803 Aug 13 (Box 26, Folder 370, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Copy of a royal decree, addressed to the viceroy of Mexico, stating that members of the clergy condemned by ecclesiastical tribunals were not beneficiaries of the pardon (indulto) issued by the King on 10 June 1796. 1800 Mar 27 (Box 26, Folder 371, Reel 24)
  - Title: Viceregal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copy of a viceregal decree ordering compliance with a royal decree which established that prelates were to conduct elaborate censuses of the population, including churches and their membership. Includes the royal decree dated 29 April 1800. 1802 Jun (Box 26, Folder 372, Reel 24)
  - Title: "Copia de la carta con que dio respuesta en 11 de septiembre de 1800 el excelentísimo señor virrey a la solicitud de la ciudad de México sobre permiso para que hubiese corrida de toros por la entrada de Su Excelencia." Place: Mexico City. Description: The reception of colonial authorities consisted of formal ceremonies and festive entertainments. One of the most popular entertainments was the bullfight, usually organized by city councils. In 1800, the new viceroy, Félix Berenguer de Marquina, interrupted that tradition. In this copy of his letter to the Mexico city council, Marquina denies permission for the bullfight, considering it a spectacle contrary to the morality of society and expensive for the Royal Treasury. 1800 Sep 11 (Box 26, Folder 373, Reel 24)
  - Title: Report by the civil attorney for the Royal Audiencia. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a report by the civil attorney for the Royal Audiencia of Mexico to the viceroy, Félix Berenguer de Marquina, commenting on the performance of Juan Domingo de Urriza, administrator of the Royal Treasury in the jurisdiction of Teutitlán del Camino, Orizaba. 1800 Nov 12 (Box 26, Folder 374, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree addressed to the Royal Audiencia of Mexico, dated 17 December 1800, noting that the viceroy had approved a license for Friar Isidoro Escalera to act as a visitor for the Mercedarian order in the Mexican viceroyalty. Includes a written acceptance of the royal decree by the Royal Audiencia. 1803 Dec 13 (Box 26, Folder 375, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decrees. Places, San Ildefonso, Aranjuez. Description: Copies of two royal decrees: the first, regulating the attendance of the viceroy of Mexico at the religious ceremonies in honor of the Virgin of Guadalupe; the second, on judicial immunity of foreigners (fuero). 1800-1801 (Box 26, Folder 376, Reel 24)
  - Title: Title of commissary. Place: Mexico. Description: Copy of a title of commissary for the collection of the ecclesiastical subsidy. The text constitutes a form to be completed when nominating commissaries. 1800-1801 (Box 26, Folder 377, Reel 24)
  - Title: Documents on montepío of assessors. Places: Mexico City, Veracruz. Description: Copies of documents related to the montepío for intendant's assessors. The montepío was a Spanish charitable fund set up to assist widows and orphans. 1800-1807 (Box 26, Folder 378, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree, addressed to the viceroy of Mexico, on the nomination and salaries of assistants to priests (coadjutores). 1801 Aug 4 (Box 26, Folder 379, Reel 24)
  - Author: Ximénez Barragán, Narciso. Title: Legal writ. Place: Puebla. Description: Copy of a legal writ by Narciso Ximénez Barragán related to the judicial proceedings against Jerónimo de la Trinidad, Indian of the town of San Juan de Atengo, for the murder of Urbano Martín. 1801 Oct 10 (Box 26, Folder 380, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Two copies of a royal decree, issued on 20 November 1801, ordering that administration of testamentary legacies lay with civil judges, when controversy over jurisdiction existed between them and ecclesiastical tribunals. The copies are addressed to the cathedral chapter of Mexico and to Antonio Bergosa, bishop of Oaxaca. 1803 (Box 26, Folder 381, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Copy of a royal decree, addressed to the Royal Audiencia of Mexico, stating that the administration of testamentary legacies and the determination of the validity of testaments were to be made by royal judges and not by ecclesiastical tribunals. 1801 Nov 20 (Box 26, Folder 382, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decrees. Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Copy of three royal decrees, complete and partial, concerning the rents of canons (5 December 1801), colonial militias (n.d.) and confiscation of merchandise for improper registration (n.d.). 1802 (Box 26, Folder 383, Reel 24)
  - Title: Royal decrees. Places: Aranjuez, Madrid, Badajoz. Description: Copies of royal decrees on the dispute between the bishop and the indentand of Puebla; the service in rural parishes by priests; the judicial privileges of members of colonial militias; administration of chaplancies; collection of tithes; and episcopal visits. 1801 (Box 26, Folder 384, Reel 24)
  - Title: "Rexistro de los nombramientos y gracias soberanas o superiores a favor de los empleados en gefes y subalternos de esta aduana principal de León. Libro segundo." Place: Leon. Description: Book containing nominations for positions in the custom office in Leon. 1801-1860 (Box 26, Folder 385, Reel 24)